Guide to the Walter Lionel Pforzheimer Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Walter Lionel Pforzheimer collection
1487-1997
MS 14
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
The collection contains three parts: autograph documents and letters, Bowling Green Press records, and contemporary American newspapers. The most significant part of the collection are the ca. 45 autograph items relating to French military history from the Middle Ages through the 19th century. There are also 12 carbon copies (signed) of letters from Theodore Roosevelt to various recipients (1911-1913) together with notes, extracts, and full copies of Roosevelt speeches (1912-1913). Series II of the collection is made up of the records of the Bowling Green Press of New York City, of which Arthur Pforzheimer was treasurer. Included are correspondence, ledgers, account books and incorporation papers. Contemporary memorabilia collected by Walter Pforzheimer is comprised of the initial issues of the Washington Times and U.S.A. Today and the final issue of the Washington Star.
Pforzheimer, Walter L. (Walter Lionel), 1914-2003
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Walter L. Pforzheimer, 1940-1982, 1998.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Documents and Papers II. Bowling Green Press Records III. Newspapers and additional material.
Scope and Contents
The Pforzheimer Collection in Manuscripts and Archives comprises three series: Documents and Papers, Bowling Green Press Records, and Newspapers. Series I is composed of approximately seventy items relating primarily to the military history of France from the Middle Ages through the nineteenth century. Also of special interest is a group of Theodore Roosevelt letters (signed carbon copies) and speeches. Series II consists of correspondence, ledgers, account books, invoices, credit memoranda, and papers filed by the Bowling Green Press to achieve incorporation. The papers in this series cover the years 1927-1931, and appear to have been the property of Arthur Pforzheimer, treasurer of the company. Series III contains first and final issues of several American newspapers dating from the 1980s.
Other material given to Yale by Walter Lionel Pforzheimer (Yale College 1935, Yale Law School 1938) housed in this library include the Wendell Willkie Presidential Campaign Papers and a number of important single manuscripts which are catalogued individually in the Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection. Mr. Pforzheimer holds a corporation appointment as Advisor on Special Collections, Yale University Library, and specializes in collecting Moliere, rare bindings, Americana, copyright law, and books on espionage and intelligence. He has been a member of the Board of Trustees of the Yale Library Associates since 1936 and as a lawyer is a specialist in the law of copyright and literary property. After serving with Air intelligence during the Second World War, Mr. Pforzheimer assisted in the establishment of the Central Intelligence Agency and worked as its legislative counsel. In 1960, he was appointed Special Assistant to the Assistant Director for Central Reference of the Agency.
The manuscripts in Series I of this collection were donated to the library during the 1940s and 1950s; those of Series III during the 1980s. The Bowling Green Press Records were donated in 1957 by Mr. Pforzheimer as a separate collection, Manuscript Group Number 927, and were incorporated into the present collection in 1983.
Biographical / Historical
Yale graduate, lawyer, adviser on special collections to Yale University Library.
Publishers and publishing -- New York (State); Europe; France -- History, Military; Autographs; Baker, Borman L.; Béthune, Philippe de, comte de Selles et de Charost, 1561-1649; Bigelow, William Sturgis, 1850-1926; Bloomer, Millard J.; Bourne, Jonathan, 1855-1940; Cochems, Henry F. (Henry Frederick), 1875-; Custine, Renaud Philippe, d.1794; Day, Jeremiah, 1773-1867; Digeon, Alexandre-Elizabeth-Michel, 1771-1826; Digges, Thomas Attwood, 1742-1821; Dommanget, B.; Donzelot, François-Xavier, 1764-1843; Dumas, Mathieu, comte, 1753-1837; Dumoustier, Pierre, 1771-1831; Ferry, Paul, 1591-1669; Fouchʹe, Joseph, duc d'Otrante, 1759-1820; Harris, Julian LaRose, 1874-1963; Hill, Henry, 1795-1892; Holbert, Hugh; Lanfredini, Giovanni, d.1487?; Medici, Lorenzo de', 1449-1492; More, A.Y.; Munsey, Frank Andrew, 1854-1925; Muy, Jean Baptiste Louis Philippe de Felix Sante Maine, 1755-1820; Oilliamson, Marie-Gabriel-Eléonore, comte d', 1738-1830; O'Neill, Charles P., 1842-; Orléans, Louis Philippe Joseph, duc d', 1747-1793; Pforzheimer, Walter L. (Walter Lionel), 1914-2003; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946; Plunkett, Horace Curzon, Sir, 1854-1932; Purdy, Milton Dwight, 1866-; Richelieu, Armand-Emmanuel du Plessis, duc de, 1766-1822; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Sansey, François; Sheerin, James, 1865-1933; Sully, Maximilien de Béthune, duc de, 1559-1641; Sutherland, James; Thierry, Amédée Simon Dominique, 1743-1803; Toussaint Louverture, 1743-1803; Vessey, Robert S. (Robert Scadden), 1858-1929; Wallace, Henry W., 1836-; Wheeler, Benjamin Ide, 1854-1927; Willard, Charles Dwight, 1866-1914; Yeiser, John O. (John Otho), 1866-1928; Bowling Green Press (New York, N.Y.)
- Documents and Papers, Series I
  - Walter L. Pforzheimer
    - Application for refund of retirement deduction, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - In Memorium notice for Richard Chapin, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Europe
    - Béthune, Philippe, Comte de (d. 1649) (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Document signed by him, 1605 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Letter to Maximilien de Béthune Sully (Grenoble), 1645 September 18 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Cartier to Maximilien de Béthune Sully, letter signed by him, 1628 January 5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Emperor Charles V - xerox copy of letter, coded in part, to Governor of Milan (Augsburg), 1578 July 5 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Constantole Rebecque, Henri Benjamin; letter to unidentified Marquis (Paris), 1818 March 22 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Custine, Renaud Philippe, d. 1794, General, Commander in Chief of Army of the Rhine
      - List of batallion paymasters with the sums of money due to them, 1792 August 8 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Message signed by him, 1792 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Order signed by him (Mainz) with a message from Pierre Blanchard on the back, 1792 December 20 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Dalmatie, Nicholas-Jean de Dieu, duc de; letter to unidentified minister of French government (Chargy les Bols), 1861 November 19 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Dieche, General, Commander of the Strasbourg Division of the Army of the Rhine; message signed by him, 1794 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Digeon, Alexandre - Élisabeth-Michel, Visconte, 1771-1826
      - Letter to an unidentified correspondent (Bayonne), 1809 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Letter introducing George Capadoce (Cuença), 1813 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Military order signed by him (Vincennes), 1820 August 20 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Order signed by him, 1833 July 25 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Document signed by him (Strasbourg), 1833 August 24 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Document signed by him (Metz), 1840 March 16 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Dommanget, B, General; letter to Lieutenant General Count Payot (Paris), 1830 December 10 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Donzelot, Francis Xavier, Brigadier General, Chief of Staff; letters to Citizen Gauthier, Colonel of the 37th Regiment at Brest, 1804 April 26, 1805 February 23 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Dumas, Mathieu, Comte, 1753-1837
      - Letter concerning the Blanchard affair (Paris), 1801 August 23 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Testimony (Paris), 1810 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Letter to the Prefect of the Department of Lower Loire (Paris), 1830 October 23 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Letter introducing Baron Delaitre (Paris), 1831 December 21 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Letter of indemnity (Paris), n.y. August 21 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Dumoustier, Pierre, Comte, 1771-1831; letter to Lieut. General Baron Durrieu (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Ferry, Paul (1591-1669) to Maximilien de Béthune Sully; letters signed by him
      - 1636 July 30 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - 1638 August 4 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - 1639 August 14 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - 1642 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - 1642 June 26 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - 1647 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Fouché; Joseph, Duc d'Otrante, Minister of Police; letter to Commanding General of the 17th Military Division at Paris, 1800 August 11 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Medici, Lorenzo de; letter to Giovanni Lanfredini (d. 1487?), Master Orator at Florence, 1487 December 26 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Muy, Jean Baptiste Louis Philippe de Felix Sainte Maine; Document of Recruiting Council concerning Louis Breviere, 1805 September 21 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Oilliamson, Marie Gabriel Eleanor, Comte de Lieutenant General of the Army of the King; letter to the Minister of Finance (Paris), 1816 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Orléans, Louls Philippe Joseph, Duke of; document signed by him, 1785 August 30 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Richelieu, Armand Emmanuel, Duke; letter to (M. L'Huilliet), 1821 August 5 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Sansey, François to Maximilien de Béthune Sully; concerning efforts to obtain a Papal Bull, 1625 December 27 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Sully, Maximilien de Béthune, Duc de (1559-1641)
      - Legal document, 1621 August 14 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - Inquiry concerning donation of memorial door at St. Paul Church in Paris, 1634 November 20 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - Unidentified copy of document, n.y. July 24 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      - Copy of letter to unidentified, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Thierry, Amédee, S.D. (1797-1873); letter to "My dear colleague". (missing 9/14/94), n.y. January 27 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Toussaint Louverture, Francois Domenique; ration list for a five day period, (Dec. 25-30), Santo Domingo, 1802 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Histoire de France, anonymous manuscript compilation of excerpts from old chronicles; bound together with the abridgement of the Annalesde Bourgogne, calendar of birthdays of various princes and peers of France, copies of various documents and petitions submitted to the Kings of France, memoirs of d'Esperon, and various minor writings, 1649 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - America
    - Day, Jeremiah to Henry Hill, 1848 July 26 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Digges, Thomas A. to Mr. Baggot, 1817 May 30 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Porter, Noah to Daniel Reed Larned, 1873 May 3
      General
      (Transferred to Noah Porter Papers, Mss 1131)
    - Roosevelt, Theodore - Letters:
      - To Dr. W. Sturges Bigelow, 1913 April 30 (Box 2, Folder 51)
      - To Millard J. Bloomer, 1911 December 5 (Box 2, Folder 52)
      - To Jonathan Bourne, Jr, 1911 January 2 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      - To Julian Harris, 1912 August 1 (Box 2, Folder 54)
      - To Frank A. Munsey, 1912 January 16 (Box 2, Folder 55)
      - To Gifford Pinchot, 1912 November 13 (Box 2, Folder 56)
      - To Sir Horace Plunkett, 1912 August 3 (Box 2, Folder 57)
      - To James Sheerin, 1912 August 22 (Box 2, Folder 58)
      - To Benjamin Ide Wheeler, 1912 November 20 (Box 2, Folder 59)
      - To Charles Dwight Willard, 1911 April 28 (Box 2, Folder 60)
      - To John O. Yeiser, 1912 November 20 (Box 2, Folder 61)
      - To R.S. Vessey, et al, 1913 January 22 (Box 2, Folder 62)
      - No addressee or date given, penciled notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Roosevelt, Theodore - Writings:
      - City Club of St. Louis, Manuscript notes of an address, 1912 March 28 (Box 2, Folder 64)
      - Chicago, extracts from a speech on Negro question, 1912 August 6 (Box 2, Folder 65)
      - Minneapolis, speech against Political Bossism, 1912 March 29 (Box 2, Folder 66)
      - Belgium, Ghent, extracts from a speech delivered at the luncheon given in honour of a deputation of English journalists, 1913 May 12 (Box 2, Folder 67)
      - Speech defining the principles of Democratic Government, no title, place or date, undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
      - Speech comparing problems of Lincoln's day to his present, title and first three pages lacking, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
- Bowling Green Press Records, Series II
  - Correspondence, 1928 March-December (Box 2, Folder 70-71)
  - Papers related to incorporation, 1927, undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Ledger, 1927-1928 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Invoices, 1927-1929 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Cash book, 1927-1931 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Credits, 1928-1929 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Miscellaneous financial papers, 1928, undated (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Oversize material
    - Common stock book, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Preferred stock book, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - "Book of Account,", 1927-1930 (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Account book, 1928-1930 (Box 3, Folder 81)
- Newspapers, Series III
  - Washington Star, final issue, 1981 August 7 (Box 3, Folder 81A)
  - Washington Times, final issue, 1982 March 1 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - USA Today, first two issues, 1982 September 15, 16 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - The Intelligence Profession Series
    - No. 1, Hans. Moses, "The Clandestine Service of the Central Intelligence Agency,", 1983 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - No. 2, John S. Warner, "National Security and the First Amendment,", 1984 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - No. 3, Thomas Polgar, "The KGB: An Instrument of "Soviet Power,", 1984 (Box 3, Folder 85)
- Additional Material, Accession 1998-M-105
  Scope and Contents
  This addition consists primarily of printed material pertaining to the fiftieth anniversary of the 1947 founding of the Central Intelligence Agency.
  - Central Intelligence Agency [fiftieth anniversary] printed material, 1997
    - "Trailblazer Award" [includes letter to award recipient] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Celebrate the Present" [program for employee day] (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Factbook on Intelligence: 50th Anniversary Edition" (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "The Cold War: 50 Years of Silent Conflict" [brochure for exhibit of espionage paraphernalia] (Box 1, Folder 2)